hello everyone it's may 26 2022. it's
the fourth week
of the first cohort of the octave
textbook group
we're in our first discussion of chapter
two
today we're going to go over the
questions that are posted for
chapter two
then we'll see where that takes us
and what ideas of the book have been
explored
and that'll be the main focus
also just a note on the math learning
group
those meetings have been occurring on 19
utc on wednesdays
and so in the math learning group you'll
find information about how to
participate
you'll find and be able to edit
resources on learning different topics
so this is a really helpful activity if
people want to share the resources that
help them learn about different ideas
and that will help people
search for a video about this
we have a notation table
that will help us as we start to look at
the notation more
there's some
math learning basic questions
like around math anything related to the
textbook content
can go in the main questions math
learning group is part of the real
textbook group so these are not the
questions to be answered like the other
ones that we're going to go to are but
this is just about math and then also
there's some math oriented overviews
like i wrote this summary of the first
two-thirds of chapter two so if people
want to be like
continuing to distill
and represent what they're learning and
what they're asking that's all good
okay
any other
um
notes that anybody wants to add before
we start to go into the questions
you can raise your hand or you can type
it in the chat
okay
so we're in the first week of discussing
chapter two the low road to active
inference
so just to kind of warm us up
um
what is the low road
[Music]
yeah the low road is
uh
the bayesian brain approach right here
um is the like proximate
next like big concept i guess
previous
but it's kind of based on i guess yeah i
mean you could see right in the picture
like it's based on basic it's like
mathematical i the way i conceptualize
it is like
literally
uh
you know the low road meaning like
um very primitive
very mathematical very
like hyper analytical
foundational kind of
you know an analysis way of looking at
it i guess
that's not necessarily living or
anything like that right
whereas the high road is kind of more
about
the other side of that
right
okay
so we're going to be
learning about the high road and low
road those are the two paths that are
offered in chapter two and three
of the book so hopefully
again like
it would be awesome to have as many
people as possible speak and feel
welcome to share their views during this
session
so everyone is especially encouraged to
put questions or comments in the chat or
raise their hand to speak
or find other times to have synchronous
communications and especially to make
contributions to the coda but really
appreciate that everyone has come out to
go through these discussion
questions
so we're going to now go to the
that have been placed into the questions
table
and just the more questions the better
they can be super short it can be
anything that you're having uncertainty
about
if you come across a table or a figure
or sentence in the text and you have a
question
please write the question down
it will be extremely extremely helpful
it doesn't have to be
with extensive
um
references or citations it can just be
what did this mean if you're uncertain
about something
and then if you were certain about it
you could still write a question like
what would you ask somebody to test or
to understand what they understood about
it okay
so we're gonna start
with this first
most upvoted question but there's still
time
in this session and also
till next week in our next session on
chapter two to add more questions if you
wrote them down somewhere else and also
to upvote questions but we're just going
to start with the most interestingly
voted questions
what is the relevance
of the support
and surprise
for the different probability
distributions in table 2.1
so what does anyone see in table 2.1
and what are support and surprise
people mic yes
so table 2.1 looks to me
excuse me like
a guide for selecting distributions um
if you're
building out one of these models
with support saying
uh you know what set of
numbers would fit
within this distribution selection and
then if you chose this distribution
how would you look at the support
equation for it
yeah
so if you chose this distribution how
would you look at the surprise component
of it
and we're going to get to surprise and
busy in surprise
in the coming questions
so support
using the
definition pulled here from wikipedia
the support of the function
is the subset of the x-axis like the
domain
where there's a y value that's not zero
so it's where the function is non-zero
defined
the gaussian
the
normal
bell curve distribution
has non-zero support
at all numbers
fancy r
and then other distributions have
different
variable different values that they're
having non-zero values at like the gamma
distribution
is defined over the interval from zero
to infinity
so if it was like how many of this thing
do you have
that might be a reason to use a
distribution
that's only positive numbers
or if you were wanting something that
could have positive or negative numbers
of any size the gaussian is a
distribution
and then another
one that's like a relevant support
difference would be like the dear schley
being defined only within the zero to
one interval
which helps connect it to probabilities
so the support is where
that function that distribution
family is defined and then
what is
the surprise
does anyone know the name of the little
squiggle they are using to represent
surprise
i think it's called fracture i
aka fancy eye
um
the first we're going to come to the
definition of surprise in a coming
question
but um and without going into every
variable and trying to
overlearn something
the surprise of a given observation like
a data point let's just think about the
gaussian
x
is the observed data point
and mu is like the mean of that
normal distribution which is also the
mode so it's like the center of that
distribution
and then this
capital pi is a variance estimator i
believe here
so how surprised one should be by a new
data point coming in
is
related to the difference between that
new data point and the mean so if the
new data point were exactly on the
center of the distribution
this whole term is going to go to zero
so one should not be surprised at all
by exact
data points on the mean of the
distribution but any data point that has
not exactly on the mean is going to have
some non-zero value
and so it's going to be a function of
how far the data point is from the mean
and
some scaling by the variance
so
if we were expecting 100
with a variance of 10
versus 100 with a variance of one
in one case like getting 101 is like a
one sigma event it has a z score of one
just speaking loosely here
whereas in the um case of it having a
variance that's very small
then that might be more surprising
any other
comments that people have on table 2.1
uh i have a question
set
yeah
so
while i was reading through the chapter
uh there
so okay uh
going back to section 2.2 right
perception as inference
so when he says when they say that the
brain is a protective machine or a
statistical organ that in first affects
external states of the world
uh
okay here's my question
because i'm primarily from a telecom
background
so
most of our
things
are to get messages across between two
distance transmitters uh receiver right
so we build noise models so without any
noise you don't get signal
so you need to know what a noise model
looks like
and then
you know so for example if the power
spectrum of the signal is what you
expect from let's say you're using a
gaussian
distribution of noise right so if it's
the same as you expect from the gaussian
uh you do nothing so that's just noise
so you don't classify the data that's
coming
in if it is more than this then
uh okay so
there might be something interesting
about this there might be some signal
here so we define the signal to noise
ratio
a lot of this chapter seems to be
dealing with the fact that
uh
we by default know what the signal looks
like
so there's no attempt to build a noise
model here
that would be like okay so uh maybe the
sensor in this case our eyes for example
or
has some
parameters for it right it can detect
between
uh
say a bandwidth
well okay so it can detect a light
between certain frequency ranges but
maybe it performs very well in a certain
frequency range and not others there's
more error
in
other frequency ranges right so the
noise model should incorporate such
things
imperfections in the sensor
imperfections in the connections between
the sensor and processing equipment
but but there's no attempt to do that in
this entire chapter so i'm just curious
as to
what exactly is the predictive machine
here
what what is being predicted here
great question and in general every
question that people have
they're going to be 100 times more
impactful
if they can be written down
this is just the second chapter it's
introducing us to the essence of
starting with just bayes equation
it's the first equation here starting
with the the foundation of
increasingly advanced noise filtering
approaches so check out live stream 43
to see how calm and filter and advanced
multi-level bayesian filtering schemes
are used and learned and fit with free
energy minimization and so on but you're
right that is not approached in this
chapter
because it's starting with the essence
of bayes equation
and then going to build towards
another kernel
which is going to be
the kernel of the variational free
energy
and then that in this one layer case is
going to be able to be elaborated and
parameterized and fit within nested
models to accommodate like
learning on hyper parameters learning of
noise models and so on but it is not in
this chapter
okay yeah so i was just i'm sorry if i
threw us off track no so it's perfect
but
they're good questions and then jakob
asked
what do you think of the surprise the
distributions involving a sum product of
the product probability distributions
except for gamma
actually i guess the gaussian kind of as
well
um
yeah maybe i'm thinking about this wrong
but uh i thought that the surprise
was
like the
i guess the information gain
um or
equivalent
and so for the for the gaussian and the
gamma distributions it's always for one
single
one single element
uh of the distribution for one x
but for the multinomial and dirichlet
there's something over all of the
possible probabilities which makes it i
guess an entropy function
but
is there
is there a difference
for example one could have a
multi-dimensional gaussian a
two-dimensional gaussian
and then the surprise for the
would be represented as a sum over
the different dimensions so they've
shown the gaussian and the gamma
in the uni-dimensional case and the
multinomial in the dirichlet in a
multi-dimensional case
so in that case is it
um
i thought that x was just one element of
the domain
so that's not necessary so
x is just
if we think of the gaussian as
this kind of bell shaped curve
on the x and y axis we really want the
f of x value to get like the gaussian
value but x is
just the input value
is that correct leave that as accurate
because yes x is the domain of the
function and then the sum is over eyes
so if we had a multinomial gaussian or
multi-dimensional gaussian in eye
dimensions then it would have a sum over
eyes
yeah so if
but wouldn't uh
i guess i still have uncertainty about
why we don't do that for the single uh
single-dimensional gaussian as well
because
if we want to
if we take just one point
on the gaussian i
understand why that would have a certain
surprise but then
in the same way
if we take one point in the dirichlet
distribution
wouldn't that also shouldn't that also
have an equivalent
equation for surprise
why why in the dirichlet
dirichlet distribution are we summing
over
all the i's
but not for the but not but in the
gaussian we are considering just one
point on the probability distribution
or maybe is maybe dirichlet is
multi multi-dimensional and
that's the reason
i think this the uni-dimensional case
would be just without this sigma i
it would just be this
but if anyone has any other
thoughts especially if they want to
contribute them in like writing to
improve our understanding that'd be
awesome
let's continue to next question
in section 2.4 they write we now
introduce the simple but fundamental
advance offered by active inference this
starts from the same inferential
perspective discussed above but extends
it to consider action as inference
in your own words what is the simple but
fundamental advance offered by octave
inference
so what would anyone
write
or like to share
what is the advance of active inference
so is it uh just bringing action into
the equation
so
uh
predictive coding and
bayesian brain are specifically about
perception
visual visual perception
um i think the key thing with active
inference is that it's um well it's not
just that it brings action into the
equation it's that it treats them as
essentially the same thing that that
kind of united
um
under as part of the same process
which i think is which i think is kind
of a new development
thanks for the awesome answer
ali
uh yeah i think uh alan barthold or
bartholos in the brain's sense of
movement
uh is a
has a particularly
uh relevant um
description of action and perception
and uh he writes that perception is
simulated action
and i think that really speaks to
uh the advance made by uh active
inference i mean uh the integration of
action and perception uh or uh in other
words uh as barthold claims the
simulation
of
action and perception
is
i guess a really novel development
i think i read something
but i i can't remember where i read it
but i i think it was roughly that on
these existing bayesian brain theories
um
an aid an agent perceives in order to
act whereas under active inference and
agent acts
action kind of precedes perception
so it active inference essentially flips
this
traditional schema in terms of
which one feeds into the other
yeah i was just gonna say that uh yeah
adding on to
bringing action into the equation it
flips it like uh
there's no
where to where do your priors come from
where do the hyper parameters get
specified like where does the model
start where does where is the agency
kind of in
all of these other models
it's really uh no accordance for that or
it's hard to it's like very emergent
because here it's like very explicitly
specified
some affordance for that
thanks brock uh mike and then anyone
else who raises their hand
yeah so i'm thinking if you have priors
you have some prior assumptions
then
um
do you necessarily need to take action
in order to
sort of envision what your perception
might be so it's almost like getting
into imagination or something like that
you have a set of priors
that can drive uh
what you imagine your perception to be
before any action is taken
great question blue
so i think um
that this was like elaborated on a lot
in section
2.7 when they talk about um pursuing a
policy
um because there's consequences
like when we're planning and making
predictions that has consequence
consequences for both our
perception and our action
um like when i mean even just planning
even in a conversation when someone says
oh have a nice like have a nice day as
expected at the end of that but like
have a nice rabbit would be like what
like you're you're not expecting that
that to come at the end of that that
sentence so so when you plan it
interferes with your
perception because you didn't plan for
them to say have a nice rabbit right but
it also interferes with with your um
action and so i think like this the um
the like novelty or enhanced aspect of
active inference
loops into the fact that
perception and action are continually
impacting one another
yes
thanks blue
um
these are some of the core
memes and themes and it really is
important to understand how active
inference is similar and different
than other
work in this area like variational
bayesian inference is not introduced by
active inference
bayesian models of perception is not
introduced by active inference
bayesian models of action is not
so it's about finding what has been done
to understand what is being offered
and then whether one chooses to take
this like
history of science development of
science
view
or we kind of just want to state plainly
what it is without wondering what the
advance relative to other frameworks is
these are all really critical ideas like
the signal processing framework was
brought up earlier
and predictive processing predictive
coding
anticipatory systems
are often
purely
about sense
and
just to give one thought on that it kind
of makes sense for a video encoding
algorithm for example because every
piece of the camera is in focus
but
vision requires action
and so that's where we're going to be
bringing in all these other important
concepts
like
attention sensory attenuation
and
the active decision making component
of vision to resolve uncertainty
which is what gives rise to a generative
visual field
that seems like there's color everywhere
and seems like there's high resolution
everywhere
though that is not
the incoming sensory information
so
by fully taking this generative modeling
perspective on perception
which
um in live stream number 43.0 maria did
an awesome job of connecting this
even before helmholtz and kant
it's plato's cave
and it's part of this
long discussion about perception
and
action could be a variable
so
there's perceiving and then if action is
a variable then active inference is
providing
not just a unified framework
like a bayesian graph framework
for some variables that are interpreted
as perception and some variables that
can be interpreted as action selection
or policy planning
but
there's a tractable approximation
by shifting from the in bringing this
answer by shifting from an exact
solution to the mathematical problem
bayesian inference
to an approximate solution
variational free energy which is going
to provide a bound
on some
quantity
that might be intractable to compute
so it's going to give a heuristic
for the action perception cycle
but this is a really
great question
so people can continue to return to it
because people will probably ask us for
a long time to come
how is this different than blank or what
is active inference
these are some of the things that we
would want to have in mind ali
yeah again going back to bartow
and
his definition of perception as
simulated action
i think it uh also relates nicely to uh
marla ponti's phenomenology marlopanti
uh has a famous
statement and uh as uh has a famous
insight as
vision is the brain's way of touching uh
and so
you see
uh for instance we
as we
move around space as we uh construct our
sense of spatiality
uh i mean or
our sense of temporality or everything
else uh
we don't just begin with the
representation of space or time uh i
mean the image of
movement uh constructs because we move
and not as a consequence of our movement
thanks and
we'll
um
continue with the questions but that's
an awesome area to go into with
phenomenology with 4e cognition extended
embedded in culture et cetera et cetera
and many many of the live streams and
papers have been on those areas so it's
cool to bridge from formal models
of perception cognition and action
into
qualitative and philosophical areas
okay
and then oh thanks for
adding that
the idea of interrelated action and
perception has been around in cognitive
science for a long time
like
dynamical systems theory and inactivism
emphasize that but active inference
brings a coherent formalism to the table
which is a nice advance
well said
next question
figure 2.2
figure 2.2 illustrates why as a result
of an internal
generative model x and an external
generative process
x star
in order to measure surprise wouldn't we
need another value of y i.e a separate y
that encodes prior beliefs
if y can be objectively measured from
external signals is there a third y
that's considered the observation
first
i'd like to actually go to this question
about two notions of surprise
so um because
they might come to bear on this action
perception loop once we move from just
bayes equation
and calculating surprise on parametric
distributions
to thinking about
prior updating and cognitive entities
with the generative model that
constitutes a prior with incoming
information coming in
we're going to start to see why this
notion of surprise and bayesian surprise
are similar and different so
using the apple frog example
so the unobserved hidden state the
latent state of the world is whether
there is an apple or a frog
in a bag for example or just in this
person's area
and then
what can be observed just speaking
coarsely
is it can jump or not
and we can totally go down the rabbit
hole with what is truly observed and
things like that but this is just what
are in the context of this model the
unobserved state is the actual identity
of the object and the observation is
going to be the action
or not
we take the opportunity to unpack two
different notions of surprise both of
which are important
the first we refer to simply as surprise
it's the negative log evidence
where evidence is the marginal
probability of observations
so we saw that first sense of surprise
with the fracture i
in
the previous table we looked at
the second notion of surprise is
referred to as bayesian surprise
this is a measure of how much we have to
update our beliefs following an
observation
in other words bayesian surprise
quantifies the difference between a
prior and a posterior probability
what are the similarities and
differences between the two notions of
surprise
okay we'll
see what has been said and then
hear what other people are thinking
um so
page 20 they wrote
that
bayesian surprise scores the amount of
belief updating as opposed to surprise
which is simply how unlikely or likely
that observation was
so in that gaussian case the surprise is
like about one data point coming in
given how the distribution's
parameterized right now
how surprising was that one data point
and then bayesian surprise is going to
be about how much that distribution
is updated
after processing that data point
similarities they both depend on how
well the agent's generative model
matches the external world
and they're both measuring surprise
or bayesian surprise in the same units
which are information theoretic
quantities of information i.e gnats or
bits differences plain surprise
marginalizes over all the models degrees
of freedom under the model's prior
distribution over its adjustable
parameters
that would be
great for someone to unpack what does it
mean to marginalize over the model's
degrees of freedoms
and then bayesian surprise lets the
model choose the best set of parameters
it can to fit the observed data
and then
measures how much
of an update that was
um mike and then and then blue and then
only
yeah under the first similarity i'm
wondering if um it's
this dependency on how well the agent's
generative model matches their
perception of the external world as
opposed to matches the external world
agree with that great
addition
um
blue and then only
okay i think my hand was just left over
left up okay ellie
uh well i believe that the plain
surprise is a kind of
raw statistical surprise but bayesian
surprise in a
as a kind of processed surprise or i'm
not sure if i'm
right in saying that
plain surprise
can
probably be described as an objective
surprise as opposed to bayesian
surprised as a subjective surprise but
as i said i'm not
sure
about the
plausibility of these descriptions
great comments um
even
the
surprise alone
still depends on the parameters
of the generative model
so it's still is within a processing or
a filtering frame
albeit a fixed one
so um they talk about like uh let's
let's look at the figure where there's a
graphical overview of this apple and the
frog
so
and this is kind of giving
some graphics and words
to fill in this apple frog example so
initially
the person has this likelihood model in
the back of their head
where they have beliefs about how likely
apples are to jump
they do it one percent of the time and
how likely frogs are to jump they do it
81 of the
time that's the likelihood that's about
how observations depend on
hidden states of the world
their prior beliefs are that there's a
10 percent chance
that the entity is a frog
and these are mutually exclusive options
there's no third option here
that would be like another category um
model structure learning on the model so
we're staying within this model for now
and they sum to one because they're a
probability
then there's an observation which is
jumping
and then
the posterior reflects the updated
beliefs
about what the entity is
and so it's like it's so much
overwhelmingly more likely that frogs
jump
that seeing something jump
updates the prior from here to here
so in this case one can calculate
the surprise of the observation
without doing any updating at all
one could just stay fixed in their prior
belief
and then
could describe how surprised they are in
gnats
by given observation
in this full bayesian cycle there is an
updating of the prior to the posterior
and then that updating
can be described in terms of how much
the prior was updated
and so that's like here the model
is updated
to the observed data this is now the
best fitting model
and then we're calculating the
difference between these two
distributions
so
um regular surprise being zero means the
data point was exactly as you expected
bayesian surprise being zero means the
distribution was not updated
high surprise means that the data point
was extremely unpredicted it was
extremely unlikely
whether or not you update your model at
all
high bayesian surprise means that the
distribution was changed a lot as a
function of seeing that happen
ali
uh well perhaps i didn't understand it
correctly but uh isn't it that isn't the
case that in uh the plane surprise or uh
more generally in the uh the
bayesian formulation of the probability
of events uh
the likelihood and both the likelihood
and the priors
are
uh somehow inherent to the phenomena
inherent to the events independent of
the observers
a great question i hope i'm not going
off on a branch here but this is related
to the difference between frequentist
and bayesian approaches to statistics
so frequentism does have
viewed from the bayesian perspective
frequentism does have priors
they're uniform priors which are not
uninformative priors they just are
uniform
and so in frequentism
we come across like the maximum
likelihood
solution or the maximum likelihood
parameter
which is just like well if all
outcomes were equally a priori likely
uniform prior
then
we would just need to evaluate the
likelihood
and find the model with the maximum
likelihood solution
bayesian
offers another degree of freedom and
says well sure you could pick a uniform
prior
that would give you the maximum
likelihood solution
or
you might want to have a prior
distribution
over that space so that if something is
twice as likely a priori and then you
observe less than 2x evidence for it
you still might want like the bayes
factor or your posterior to reflect
that one
rather than just jumping instantly to a
different maximum likelihood solution
so yes priors and likelihood are
implicit
but they're using a different ontology
than bayesian statistics
but
we're in the bays or the post-based area
now
but there's so many connections to
classical statistics
and in spm the textbook
there is
parametric classical statistics
non-parametric classical statistics
and bayesian statistics
so
they're more similar than not
it just is about seeing where one of
them is like a special case of another
or a generalization of another
okay
let's see if we can do one or two more
questions during this session
okay so let's return to the previous
question
so we're looking at figure 2 2
which is
something we're going to see different
representations of
this
entity as generative model
world or niche as generative process
and then here
the hidden states are those that are
unobserved as data
y is referring to data points that are
observed as data
there's a cognitive hidden state
which is like a prior in this generative
model and then there's some hidden state
x star
but it could have been any letter or any
shape
about the hidden state in the world
the observation
is going to everything that happens in
between here is cognition
um like the sandwich model
like
sense
think
act
that type of model is just referring to
that little boomerang data come in
cognitive processing
action selection
so we're in that figure
the question was
in order to measure surprise
wouldn't we need another value of y i.e
a separate y that includes prior belief
great
question
um
let's just assume that there is a
gaussian
generative model
so the entity has like two parameters in
its cognitive model the mean and the
variance
then y comes in
and given the parameterization of the
generative model
all that's needed is
the data point to come in
for the surprise to be calculated
so
another value is needed
but
whether we call it
abc xyz z
is just a mathematical abstraction
so yes prior beliefs are
important
the prior beliefs that can be
interpreted as the parameterizations
of the cognitive model are required
if y can be objectively measured from
external signals
is there a third y that is considered
the observation
so
one could imagine
a lot of like real world scenarios
where a more complex model would be
required you know two people looking at
the thermometer or all these different
sorts of situations
but um
unless somebody can unpack this a little
more
or explain what they were asking about
then i don't think a third why is
required mike
yeah that was my question so i can try
and unpack it um
and so sticking with the thermometer
example
at the heart of that last question is
if we have a thermometer that's
registering the temperature
um
can we consider that as sort of the the
true observation that is the actual why
um as measured by this instrument and
then therefore we can compare our sort
of internal why with the actual y
okay
so i have a really similar and related
question
um
that's like two questions down
um but it's in a different section but
let me just like place some things on
here and it goes back to like what we
were saying about like what
exactly is the hidden state so is the
hidden state the temperature and the
data is
the reading from the thermometer
that like that's like the the data y
right like the out this this y in the
middle but then like what is how i feel
hot or cold like i mean i'm perfectly
positioned to be at 75 all the time so
like
i know if it's like one degree too cold
or one degree too hot like i've got to
turn up the heat or turn it down or or
whatever
but like my registration my sensory
input is not at 75 degrees like my
sensory input is i'm hotter i'm cold and
so this this is like where i mean we
were talking about this yesterday in the
math group like there's this really
fuzzy line for me like i would love for
someone to clarify that so i do get what
you mean about like this in like
shouldn't there be another y like
there's the y out there in the world 75
degrees and then there's how i feel
about that y
okay thanks um
so
variables are not like innately tagged
with being observables or hidden states
it's a model specific
framing of what is going to be modeled
as
generated data
and what is going to be modeled as a
bayesian prior
in multi-level bayesian modeling
the priors themselves are generated from
a higher or deeper
level of the so
one can be serving in fact multiple
roles this is the minimal
prior
generated data expectation maximization
type
single layer bayesian kernel
so we're going to think about this
temperature example
there's a hidden state of the generative
process
which is going to be the temperature of
the world
latent unmodeled so this isn't even
claiming that there is such a thing as
temperature this is just the latent
unobserved temperature
that is giving rise to thermometer
readings which might have like different
sorts of noise
then there's another hidden state which
is the evaluation of temperature
and so
this is just a schematic
that's
and also the whether it one is labeled x
or y or
l or triangle
is like a norm and a convenience
but
the letter doesn't matter
itself
it it will be used mostly consistently
within the textbook
but there's only so many letters and
there's not a lot of coherence on
notation use
[Music]
um
what else could be explored here
yeah um mike and then ali
so as i keep ruminating on this which is
probably more than i should
um it seems like there can be
infinite y's right so um
to the extent that you are
taking action
which will
change your perception then you are
as a result triggering potentially new
whys in the system right
so you just have this infinite potential
for what y can be
this speaks to the composability and the
flexibility of active inference so like
y could be one pixel of visual input it
could be a 4k video why could be smell
and a 4k video why could be lidar and
this and that so why is just the
generalized input
of sense
and then action
might be related
to this in a very direct way like y
could be visual input and action could
be your eye movement
so that case is going to be explored a
lot in the book
however
it could also be you're getting
something in
and then the actions are just totally
unrelated maybe they don't
affect the hidden state the causal
process in the world at all
or maybe
actions enable different wise to enter
the picture
this is just the total essence kernel
and then
even trivial cases require
some more apparatus
ali
yeah i have a question uh
is it
correct to say that the minimization of
variational free energy aka
the surprise
is exactly equivalent to the
maximization of expectation
uh i mean is it uh
i mean the holy linear relationship
between these two uh or possibly we have
some uh
kind of plateaued areas between
these two
extremes
great question
so this is something that we'll
come to
next week in our discussions on chapter
two so
we have not
even discussed variational free energy
yet
today we talked about starting
with a low road on some of the atomic
calculations that are going to come into
play like surprise
and bayesian surprise in a bayesian
framework
and beginning to partition
active entities and their action
perception loops
in terms of a bayesian graph
that's going to be amenable to flexible
modeling of perceptive cognitive
active and out there in the world
variables variables with those
interpretations and then
variational free energy is going to come
into play
as a way to bound
surprise
so let's
have some questions in discourse and
we'll come to it next week but it's an
awesome question jessica
hi yes i have a question um
i guess related to this figure 2.0
let's say like um in regards to like how
we interpret on like what we observe so
like i understand like you have a prior
that might you know
you're anticipating
you know
something like some other people's
behavior or like how things should be
that might be different from what you
actually observe
but a lot of times at least in terms of
like when we're thinking like human
beings like it's like
an action in the world like
how you interpret it and has to do a lot
with on
your own like views or like your own
experiences and maybe that connects to
the priors and like like the
interpretation might be very different
like from people to people the
interpretation will vary a lot because
everybody has on like a lot of like
different experiences so
those could be like uh encoded i guess
in the priors um but it's not connected
per say to the
production part or maybe it is so i'm
trying to
kind of connect that idea and of
how like our personal interpretation
based on our experiences which could be
priors
make us see the
um
like
like what's happening in the world
differently
than other people and so that why would
look very different from you
than for me just because we have lived
different experiences
so it's not like a like an actual why
like it's not like you cannot really say
like
this is a fact and because it's an
interpretation at the end of the day
great question and points
yeah understanding how
the individual
setup of a given entity is related to
its past experiences and how that could
be modeled by priors
is an important
area
and um
some of those rich dynamics
are not in this
minimal nucleus
but it'll be awesome to start to think
about what does have to be
in the box here
to give rise to those kinds of dynamics
um so that's going to
end this discussion
um
next week we will also be staying in
chapter two
and taking it more towards
variational free energy and expected
free energy
so that should be
fun
we're going to in this room
transfer immediately to the dot tools
meeting so if you want to join for
activelab.tools meeting everyone is
welcome and there's no like
prerequisites or anything like that
if you want to hang around
and join tools
stay in this exact gather space
if you want to continue talking with
other people about the book
or anything else just
head up into one of the rooms above and
if anyone anyone who wants to can just
continue any discussion that they want
but in this space we're going to
continue now with tools
so
thanks everyone